If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we explore the effect
of collagen on the body
and we start with a story
about collagen supplements.
Collagen supplements have become
quite the trendy treatment
for aging skin,
available in an array of pills,
powders, and products
from bars and gummies
to collagen coffee and beer.
Social media is said to be
"inundated with paid ads
marketing
unsubstantiated claims."
What claims, if any,
can be substantiated?
The word collagen comes
from the Greek kola,
meaning "gum,"
and gen, meaning "producing."
Its gelling nature is
exemplified by Jell-O gelatin,
which is basically
just cooked collagen.
It is our most abundant protein
and the main
structural component
of most of the tissues
in our body.
For example, up to three
quarters of our skin by weight
may be pure collagen.
There are actually
dozens of different types,
but they all share
a characteristic
triple helix configuration
of coiled subunits.
What happens when we eat it?
If someone would have asked
for my educated guess
about taking collagen
before I took a deep dive
for my book How Not to Age,
I would have dismissed it
as witch-doctory woo-woo.
Eating skin for your face would
seem to make as much sense
as eating brains
to make yourself smarter
or eyeballs
to improve your vision.
After all,
when you eat proteins,
they are broken down into
their constituent amino acids,
which are then rebuilt into
any protein your body needs.
And, of all proteins to eat,
collagen is the only protein
in our food supply
that's truly incomplete.
That is, it's missing
an essential amino acid.
Other dietary proteins,
including all plant proteins,
contain all of
the essential amino acids--
in fact, that's why
they're called essential,
since animals like us
can't make them.
Collagen, though, is missing
the amino acid tryptophan.
So, the only protein source that
you couldn't live on is Jell-O,
since it effectively has
a protein quality score of zero.
But obviously that's
not all people eat;
so, significant
amounts of collagen
could be incorporated into
the diet without keeling over,
but tryptophan is special.
Randomizing people
to even a single meal
of a gelatin-based protein drink
can lead to memory impairments
within hours
due to
"acute tryptophan depletion,"
presumably due to a drop
in the brain of serotonin,
which is made from
tryptophan and doesn't just
regulate mood but learning
and memory as well.
So, the idea
of collagen supplements
never made sense to me,
but the proof is in the pudding,
or rather, perhaps,
the Jell-O.
What does the science say?
My assumption that
collagen proteins would get
completely broken down in
the digestive tract was wrong.
Feed people gelatin from
pig skin or chicken feet,
and little pieces
of collagen particles
can be found floating in
their bloodstream within hours.
Though no further tracking has
been done in humans, in rodents,
collagen fragments
from gelatin consumption
can end up in
cartilage and skin.
Now, biologically,
there is no mechanism
by which these fragments
could be directly incorporated
into new collagen,
but there may be an indirect way
collagen bits could boost
collagen deposition,
as appears to happen
in rat skin.
What about in people?
Some of the collagen studies
lack control groups.
I'm reminded of that vintage
Star Trek episode Mudd's Women,
where Kirk successfully swaps
out a youth-giving supplement
for a placebo
without the aliens noticing.
Randomized controlled trials
are scarce,
but a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of the available data
showed that,
although outcomes were mixed,
on average,
there were beneficial effects
for skin hydration,
elasticity, and roughness.
Despite some favorable results,
much of the
dermatology community
has remained skeptical,
suggesting the collagen
supplement industry may just be
flooding the zone with
poor quality, biased studies.
The studies are often funded
by collagen supplement
manufacturers,
and the overall quality of
evidence is considered to be
"limited, contradictory,"
"not particularly robust."
A 2022 review entitled
"Myths and media in oral
collagen supplementation
for the skin, nails, and hair"
in the Journal of Cosmetic
Dermatology concluded that
"Dermatologists should be aware
of the unsubstantiated
proclamations of collagen
made by companies
[which] surpass any evidence
currently supported
by the literature."
And, given
the insufficient evidence,
"collagen cannot be routinely
recommended at this time."
Moreover, the evidence
is considered to be
"particularly unconvincing"
when compared to methods more
definitely shown to have
a positive effect
on skin collagen,
such as sunscreen use,
smoking cessation,
and a healthy diet.
In our next story,
we see if collagen can beat out
placebo for knee osteoarthritis.
Nearly a millennium ago,
a medieval nun suggested eating
gelatin to reduce joint pain.
Unfortunately, when it was put
to the test in a multicenter,
randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trial,
it didn't work.
A dozen years later, looking
at knee and hip osteoarthritis,
there was still
no overall evidence
for collagen supplements
working better than placebo.
However, the latest compilation
of studies purported to show
a benefit for improving
osteoarthritis symptoms.
In one symptom index, it
appeared to help with stiffness,
but not pain or disability.
But, an overall
improvement in symptoms
and a different index of pain
were statistically significant.
If, however, you exclude
the smallest study,
whose authors were employees
of a collagen company,
all of the results
lost clinical importance,
meaning the overall effects
were unnoticeably small.
In fact, every single one was
funded by collagen companies,
or directly run
by company employees.
Another thing you'll
notice about these data
is that with this one exception,
the smaller the study,
the larger the effect.
This pattern is a common sign
of publication bias,
the tendency to do
a whole bunch of small trials,
but publish only the ones
that work to your advantage
and secretly shelve the rest.
Coupled with all of
the conflicts of interest,
concerns have been raised
that additional small studies
may have been conducted
but conveniently disappeared.
And then, other fishy findings
are that smaller doses
appeared to have larger effects,
as did using it
for a shorter amount of time.
Okay, but the last study
was published in 2016.
What's happened since then?
A comprehensive systematic
review published in 2022
was surprised to note
that the last study done
on collagen supplements
for rheumatoid arthritis
was published
more than a decade ago,
and the last osteoarthritis
study was still that 2016 one.
Why?
Well, one possible reason
is the high incidence of
adverse side effects reported
in those taking
collagen supplements,
or another reason may be
that they simply
don't work very well.
I mean, if collagen company
executives truly believed
they were selling
something that worked,
why don't they do more studies?
If they thought collagen had
a decent chance of working,
they could make out
like bandits.
The fact that they haven't
sponsored such a trial
suggests they're
not so confident
it would actually show benefit.
One study has been published
since 2016, the biggest yet,
with more than 150 people.
Funded by a collagen company,
researchers found
a significant drop in knee pain,
and a significant
improvement in knee function
among those randomized
to collagen supplements.
But they also found a
significant drop in knee pain
and improvement in knee function
in those randomized
to the placebo,
with no real difference
between them.
So, the fact that
effectively a sugar pill
worked as well as
the collagen supplements
suggests that
collagen doesn't work.
But that does raise
another point.
If you look at what
was used for controls
in the collagen studies,
it was basically
just sugar or sawdust.
So, even if collagen was found
to be helpful in some way,
there is no proof
that collagen has any effects,
beyond just being
a source of amino acids
like any other protein.
So, if any purported
collagen effect
is just a matter of increased
amino acid availability,
then why not just, like,
have some extra hummus
or something?
Finally today,
we reveal which foods may be able to increase
collagen deposition and prevent wrinkles.
As we age, the synthesis
of collagen decreases
by about 1 percent a year,
which may contribute
to the development of wrinkles.
Though we don't have evidence
that collagen is superior to any
other proteins for aging skin,
those who do want to try it
are advised to contact
the manufacturers
to clarify its source.
Most collagen supplements don't
disclose this information
and for good reason.
Terrestrial sources
can include a witch's brew
of kangaroo and rat tails,
duck feet, horse tendons,
alligator bones,
and frog skin.
Aquatic sources are mainly
from fish skins, bones, heads,
scales, fins, and entrails.
Recommended questions
for manufacturers include
"What measures were used
to protect against
contamination or adulteration?
If sourced from fish,
were low-mercury fish used?
If sourced from cows,
what steps were taken
to ensure that
no brain or nervous system
matter was included,
in order to prevent
prion disease?"
In the United States,
collagen is exempt
from FDA prohibitions
against using risky tissues
like brains--
prohibitions in place
to protect consumers
against bovine spongiform
encephalopathy,
also known as mad cow disease.
So, for food safety,
religious, ethical,
or allergy-related reasons,
there have been calls
for non-animal alternatives.
For example, 2 to 4 percent
of the population
is allergic to bovine collagen.
To solve the mad cow conundrum,
there have been calls
to genetically engineer
cattle without prions
to "offer a safe source
of collagen-based materials."
But why not just get
plants to make it?
A technique has been perfected
to produce collagen from plants,
but it has not yet reached
commercial viability.
It's hard to beat
the cost of feet.
But what about all of the vegan
collagen products on the market?
If you look closely,
you'll see the small print:
vegan collagen builder
or vegan collagen booster.
It's not actually collagen,
since collagen
is made by animals,
but you're an animal,
you make collagen.
So they're suggesting
their supplements
can boost production,
but since it appears
none of them have actually
been put to the test,
I assume it's all
a load of bunk.
But there are some
foods and nutrients
that have been investigated.
Researchers burned the butts
of 20 women with a UV lamp
before and after half of them
ate three tablespoons
of tomato paste each day
for three months.
And there was a significant
reduction in MMP-1 levels
in the derrieres of those
who had been randomized
to the tomatoes.
(That's a major
collagen-eating enzyme
that plays a role in skin aging
caused by the sun.)
Butt biopsies also show
that the amount of beta-carotene
found in about
one and a third cup
of sweet potato
can boost collagen production
as much as four-fold
within three months.
To test the effects of greens,
Korean researchers
randomized older women
to the amount of chlorophyll
found in a few tablespoons
of cooked spinach a day.
After three months,
skin biopsies showed
a significant increase
in collagen production,
accompanied by an increase
in skin elasticity
and a decrease
in facial wrinkles.
Unfortunately, this was just
a before-and-after comparison
to baseline study
with no control group,
but there have been
placebo-controlled
randomized trials,
and of kale no less!
Compared to placebo, there was
a significant improvement
in a noninvasive measure
of skin collagen status
after 10 months
of being randomized
to an extract of curly kale.
The researchers concluded
that "a healthy lifestyle
including a diet
rich in carotenoids
is the best prevention strategy
against premature skin aging."
That led to dermatology
journal commentaries
with titles like "Eat plenty
of green leafy vegetables
for protection from
the pro-aging rays of the sun,"
but might it actually be
more than that?
Sulforaphane, the cruciferous
compound in kale and broccoli,
may be able to mobilize
cellular defenses
that protect skin
against damage by UV radiation,
as well as mitigate
the premature skin aging
induced by air pollution
particulate matter,
though this was on skin cells
in a Petri dish.
Soybean compounds can increase
collagen deposition
and prevent wrinkles in mice,
but what about in people?
Given improvements
of skin aging
seen with menopausal
hormone therapy
but concerned
about the side effects,
researchers in Brazil
tried giving phytohormones,
plant hormones in the form
of soy phytoestrogens.
Twenty-nine
postmenopausal women
were given the amount
in four servings a day
of soy foods for six months.
Unfortunately,
there was no control group,
but they did take skin biopsies
before and after
and found a significant
improvement in skin thickness,
along with increased
collagen content
and elastic fibers.
The biopsies
of 25 out of 29 women
showed an increase in collagen.
You could also throw in
some vitamin C-rich foods,
as vitamin C appears
to stimulate collagen production
from human skin cells.
Defective wound healing
has long been known
as a major manifestation
of scurvy,
the vitamin C-deficiency
disease.
In fact, a remarkable series
of grisly experiments
performed on British
conscientious objectors
during World War II
involved being subjected
to cuts and stab wounds
after being randomized
to different levels
of vitamin C.
The researchers found
that the average
daily vitamin C intake
to prevent weak scar formation
was about 95 milligrams,
which is actually higher than
the current recommendations
but nothing you can't get
from half a bell pepper.
Vitamin B12 also appears
to be necessary
for maximum collagen synthesis,
which may explain why
collagen synthesis rates
appear to be about 10 percent
lower in vegetarians,
because the prevalence
of B12 deficiency
among those eating
plant-based diets is so high.
That's one of many reasons
why it's critically important
that everyone consuming
a plant-based diet
ensures a regular, reliable
source of vitamin B12.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.